YWCA of the U.S.A. Records. Record Group 4. National Conventions and Conferences
Sophia Smith Collection
YWCA of the U.S.A. Records. Record Group 04. National Conventions and Conferences
1899-2001
Young Women's Christian Association of the U.S.A.
324_rg4
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
This record group consists of planning materials, mailings, local arrangements, preparatory materials, reports, proceedings, addresses, programs, and newspaper clippings for YWCA general and regional conferences and National Conventions. General conferences were some of the primary training and information-sharing opportunities for professional and volunteer staff, and members. National Conventions were held at least every three years to share information and develop program and priorities for the Association. Actions and resolutions voted by the Convention would direct Association priorities and program for the ensuing triennium. Forms part of the YWCA of the U.S.A. Records.
Conferences
From its earliest days until the early 1970s, the YWCA of the U.S.A. put considerable effort into Conferences as a means of bringing together YWCA people, sharing information, exchanging ideas, and providing for practice in public speaking, group work, legislative action, and parliamentary procedure. A wide variety of Conferences was planned for professional and volunteer staff, and members. The materials filed in this series relate to "general" or "regional" conferences. Material about Conferences for specific types of Associations (City, Town and Country, "Colored" Branches), or "constituent" groups (Industrial, Business and Professional, Teen, Student) is filed with other material related to that work. [See RECORD GROUP 6. PROGRAM, RECORD GROUP 7. STUDENT WORK, and RECORD GROUP 8. COMMUNITY ASSOCIATIONS.]
Regional Conferences (also known as General Conferences, or National Conferences in the Regions) brought together representatives from the general membership within geographic regions. Training focused on effective administration of Community YWCAs as well as the mission of the YWCA. They provided a regular avenue for the National Office to hear issues and concerns from the various geographic regions. Regional Conferences were part of "the cycle of meetings between conventions" which allowed the Association to monitor progress toward resolutions passed at prior Conventions and develop issues for discussion at upcoming Conventions.
Though other kinds of training opportunities (workshops, institutes, seminars, round-tables, etc.) continued, traditional conferences disappeared from the YWCA program by the early 1970s when a general desire for change combined with a dramatic re-organization of the staff structure and severe financial problems made them no longer feasible or desirable.
Convention
The YWCA's National Convention was the regular meeting of the national organization and served as its legislative body. Delegates from member associations met with the National Board and national staff to share information and methods; discuss, amend, and/or affirm the purpose of the organization; "consider and adopt prioritized program for the ensuing years;" establish and amend policies and procedures for the national organization; establish standards for membership of community and student associations in the national organization; and elect the National Board to shepherd the work of the organization between Conventions. National Conventions were called by the National Board at least every three years except when prevented by travel restrictions during the two World Wars.
Actions of the Convention were determined by majority vote of the delegates. These were either "voting delegates," who were representatives from member associations, (the number of delegates an association could send to Convention was a function of the size of voting membership of that Association); or "ex-officio voting delegates," who were National Board and national staff members.
Convention "entrusts" the National Board with the management of the Association in the interim between Conventions. The National Board was responsible for hiring and directing the work of the national staff. Each National Board member served a term lasting through two Convention cycles and was eligible to stand for one additional term. One third to one half of the membership was elected at each Convention.
The challenge of "creating... a common mind which can deal wisely and adequately with complex problems in the life of the organization" out of a large group of women brought together for a few days every two or three years, lead to ever-evolving experiments with preparatory materials and meetings, small group discussions, and various other techniques to achieve effective and representational participation. Though there were enduring traditions and features, no two conventions were exactly the same.
This form of organization-major organizational decisions made at intervals of two or three years-meant that changes in national YWCA policies and procedures were slow in coming. Often when issues were brought to Convention, the result was a resolution to establish a Commission to study the situation and report to the following Convention. It was not unusual for changes to be studied and discussed through two or three Convention cycles before final decisions were reached.
Due to this deliberative process, often-cited "watershed" Convention Actions, such as the adoption of the Federal Council of Churches' "Social Ideals of the Churches" in 1920, the "Interracial Charter" in 1946, and the "One Imperative: the elimination of racism wherever it exists and by any means necessary" in 1970, were in fact the result of years of study, discussion, preparation, and incremental action. They were more a manifestation of a continuum of activity than a dramatic change of direction. YWCA Conventions regularly and repeatedly reviewed such issues as the nature of the organization's role in public policy; the diversity of its membership and leadership; religion, or the "C" in YWCA; and the role of men in the Association.
Auxiliary meetings associated with Convention, the Assemblies, were the national meetings of various YWCA Councils-the bottom-up organizations of various constituent groups within the YW: Industrial, Business and Professional, [college and university] Student, and Teen Age. These usually convened a few days before Convention.
The Convention planned for 1918 was postponed for the duration of the U.S. involvement in World War I.
The Convention planned for 1945 was cancelled at request of the federal government that convention travel be curtailed. In its stead, the National Board election was carried out by mail, and simultaneous meetings were held at each association to consider questions of importance to the whole Association and report back to the National Board. These were referred to variously as "little convention meetings" and "nation-wide discussions."
Any meetings or conferences held between Conventions provided more and less formal opportunities for the Association to measure progress toward goals set at Convention and gather ideas and opinions for future program. After World War II, the Association established a more formal "cycle of meetings between conventions" held all around the country. These were known variously as "Neighborhood Meetings," "Interim Leadership Development Meetings," "Convention Cycle Meetings," and "Mid-Triennium Conference."
After World War II, as the national organization scaled back its program activities, Convention discussion centered more on the organization's public policy platform and the internal workings of the YWCA: affiliation of associations, payment of dues, public relations, and finances. In addition, Convention served as a venue to launch such things as a new YWCA logo (1988), the 135th Anniversary exhibit (1994), and the ill-fated Worldwide Web-based "communications platform" YWLink (1998).
A series of long-range and strategic planning initiatives began circa 1988 to attempt to "transform" the YWCA for the 21st Century. These eventuated in the "Change Initiative" (1998-2000). A Special Convention was called in summer 2000 to approve an outline plan "Steps to Absolute Change." At this Special Convention, a Transition Steering Committee was charged with drafting a detailed reorganization plan for approval at a Convention the following year. The final Convention in 2001 approved the "Ten Steps to Absolute Change Transition Plan" for the restructuring of the national organization.
Staff and Committees
At the national office, Conventions and Conferences staff were in charge of business management and logistical planning of conferences and Conventions, including publicity, budgeting, scheduling, and the production of printed materials. Convention Committees planned program for Convention and any pre-Convention meetings, and solicited and gathered input from associations for resolutions and amendments to be voted on at Convention.
Administrative History
1909-23 Convention and Conference Dept
1923 Convention and Conference Division
1925-31 under Education and Research Division
1932-39 Leadership Division: business manager conferences and Convention; and General Administration
1941-70 under General Administration
c 1971-spr 1987 National Convention and Conference Office
fall 1987- Aug 1992 Convention, Meetings, and Travel Dept
fall 1992- ? Leadership Development Center staff? "Sales and Conference Planning Specialist"
Forms part of the YWCA of the U.S.A. Records.
NOTE: For the most part, the Microfilmed Records and the Original Format Records do not duplicate each other and both should be consulted. This description covers materials in both formats. See the Contents List for a folder-level inventory of the Original Format Records. See the Microfilmed Records Reel Lists for a detailed inventory of the microfilm.
The National Conferences and Conventions records consist of planning materials, mailings, local arrangements, preparatory materials, reports, proceedings, addresses, programs, and newspaper clippings.
As is the case generally with the National Association records, the bulk of the Conference and Convention materials date from 1906 to 1970, the interval covered by the microfilm of the Central File and Minutes and Reports. Though there is little conference material dated 1970 and 1988, the Convention files for these years are relatively large.
Since conferences were such a primary means of communicating and training, the minutes and reports of the department contain much about philosophy of the organization mixed with the philosophy of conferences and conventions. As with most departments, the secretaries' reports are a very rich source of information. Like most of the organization, the Conferences and Conventions Committee/Department met on an academic year schedule, taking summer months off from meetings. Since summer was the busiest season for conferences, there are especially good reports in the minutes of the first meeting in the fall.
General Conference records include preparatory mailings and publicity; agendas, programs, and daily bulletins produced during conferences; and reports on the proceedings.
Because Convention business ranges from highly detailed discussions of the internal workings of the national organization to national and international issues that were part of the organization's public policy agenda, Convention records reveal something about most any topic connected with the National organization.
A lot of printed material was generated in connection with each Convention. In addition to the Proceedings, basically a verbatim transcript of the Convention, there are many Pre-Convention materials for discussion and study. These were part of the strategy to make the meeting effective and representative. While they included the predictable hotel and travel information, there were also study documents; workbooks; rules and regulations; resolutions and amendments recommended for Convention action; and elections and balloting information.
Other materials include reports of Student, Teen, Industrial, and Business and Professional Assemblies (which met in conjunction with Convention); reports of commissions, committees, the National Board, and various departments and projects. In addition there can be texts of speeches, information about special sessions, daily bulletins, programs and scripts for skits and other dramatic presentations, worship materials; publicity; and souvenirs.
Microfilmed Records, 1899-1970 only
[see Microfilmed Records Reel List]
The Conference and Convention materials on microfilm are much more extensive than what has survived on paper. They include records of the committees and departments in charge of planning and local arrangements as well as published Convention preparation materials and reports. Also included are completed credential application forms, stenographic proceedings of the many Conventions, and some unpublished materials, such as texts of speeches, most of which are only available on the microfilm.
They can be found in:
Minutes and Reports
Conference Committee
Convention Committee
Convention and Conference Department
Subject Files
Conferences
Conventions
Original Format Records, 1906-2001, 17.5 linear feet
[see Original Format Records folder list]
Some materials microfilmed under "Conferences" can be found in paper form filed with Conventions, Training, or under the relevant program (Teen, Industrial, etc.).
Paper records include some general and historical information, Minutes and Reports of the Conferences and Conventions Committee/Department, a few files from Regional Conferences, and extensive printed and planning materials from Conventions, 1906-2001.
As with the microfilmed records, "constituent group" and program subject conference materials are filed with the group/program subject in RECORD GROUP 6. PROGRAM.
See also Related Materials.
This Record Group is divided into three Series:
I. GENERAL AND HISTORY
II. CONFERENCES
III. CONVENTIONS
The records are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection without any additional restrictions.
Access to audiovisual materials may first require production of research copies.
Additional Formats
A copy of the microfilmed records of the YWCA of the U.S.A. Records is available to borrow from the William Allan Neilson Library at Smith College via Interlibrary Loan.
To request the microfilm from our library you will need to submit the following information to your library's Interlibrary Loan department:
Author: Young Women's Christian Association of the U.S.A. National Board
Title: Records, 1876-1970 [microform]
WorldCat Accession Number: OCLC 57415795
Notes: "Call # 689" and reel number(s) you want to borrow
Full descriptions and reel lists of the microfilm are available online.
The YWCA of the U.S.A. donated a portion of its records to the Sophia Smith Collection in 1964 and the remainder in 2002 and 2003.
Civil rights movements--United States--History--20th century--Sources; Labor laws and legislation--United States--History--20th century--Sources; Labor--United States--History--20th century--Sources; Race awareness--United States; Race relations--United States
Record Groups
The YWCA of the USA Records are arranged as follows:
YWCA of the U.S.A. Records (main record)
RECORD GROUP 1. GENERAL AND HISTORY
RECORD GROUP 2. PREDECESSOR ORGANIZATIONS AND NATIONAL BOARD
RECORD GROUP 3. NATIONAL ADMINISTRATIVE OFFICE
RECORD GROUP 4. NATIONAL CONVENTIONS AND CONFERENCES
RECORD GROUP 5. INTERNATIONAL WORK
RECORD GROUP 6. PROGRAM
RECORD GROUP 7. STUDENT WORK
RECORD GROUP 8. COMMUNITY ASSOCIATIONS
RECORD GROUP 9. PHOTOGRAPHS
RECORD GROUP 10. AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS
Artifacts
The Microfilmed Records
The Oversized Materials
This Record group forms part of the YWCA of the U.S.A. Records
As the governing council of the organization, all aspects of the national association's activities are reflected in Convention records and should be consulted in concert with records related to particular departments, programs, activities.
The YWCA's magazine (The Association Monthly/Womans Press/YWCA Magazine/YWCA Interchange) contains publicity, preparation materials, and reports of conferences and conventions. See RECORD GROUP 6. PROGRAM, SERIES VI. PUBLICATIONS.
Because it was the "representative and executive" committee of the National Association, the National Board's minutes should also be consulted. See RECORD GROUP 2.
There are also Convention materials in the Public Affairs files in RECORD GROUP 6. PROGRAM, SERIES III. PUBLIC ADVOCACY.
Additional Assembly records can be found in the files for the various constituent groups which held Assemblies in RECORD GROUP 6. PROGRAM and RECORD GROUP 7. STUDENT WORK.
Files of the Music Program in RECORD GROUP 6. PROGRAM document planning for music at Convention and the assembly of song books for use at Conventions.
RECORD GROUP 10. AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS contains audio and videotapes of some conferences and conventions dating from the mid-1970s to 2001. Also included are some materials produced for Convention preparation/Cycle meetings, and miscellaneous materials produced for Conventions, such as tributes to retiring YWCA leaders.
Series Descriptions
- SERIES I. GENERAL AND HISTORY
  This series includes committee, department and office records as well as general publications about planning conferences.
- SERIES II. CONFERENCES
  This series consists of the few surviving materials about regional conferences for general membership.
- SERIES III. CONVENTIONS
  This series contains general and statistical materials about Conventions followed by files related to each Convention in chronological order from the first Convention in 1906 to the 36th Convention in 2001. Materials for each Convention are filed in chronological order with planning files (including materials related to interim meetings), followed by pre-Convention mailings and study materials, followed by materials distributed at Convention, such as programs and election ballots. Finally, there are press reports, evaluations and other post-Convention materials.
- SERIES I. GENERAL AND HISTORY
  This is the Contents List for the Original Format Records only. The reel lists for the Microfilmed Records are in a separate file. See Scope and Content note for more description.
  - General, 1910-68, n.d. (Box 265, Folder 1)
  - Department/Division/Office
    - General, 1983-90 (Box 265, Folder 2-3)
    - Minutes and reports
      - 1911-22 (Box 265, Folder 4-20)
      - 1923-Apr 1924 (Box 266, Folder 1-3)
    - Publications
      - Conference Notebook, n.d. [1947] (Box 266, Folder 4)
      - "Logistics for Planning Conferences, Institutes, Workshops," Dec 1971 (Box 266, Folder 5)
      - The YWCA's Own Baedeker: A Guide Book for Leaders of YWCA Summer Conferences, 1949 (Box 266, Folder 6)
- SERIES II. CONFERENCES
  - Financial, 1928-30 (Box 267, Folder 1)
  - Regional
    - General, 1939-69 (Box 267, Folder 2)
    - Central Region
      - General, 1945-60 (Box 267, Folder 3)
      - 1960
        - Addresses and presentations (Box 267, Folder 4)
        - Report (Box 267, Folder 5)
      - Eastern
        - General, 1951-63 (Box 267, Folder 6)
        - 1954 Report (Box 267, Folder 7-8)
        - 1966 Report (Box 267, Folder 9)
      - Southeastern, 1960 (Box 267, Folder 10)
      - Southern, 1910, 1959-60 (Box 267, Folder 11)
      - Southwest, 1960 (Box 267, Folder 12)
      - Western, 1960-66 (Box 267, Folder 13)
    - Summer: general, 1900-55 (Box 267, Folder 14)
- SERIES III. CONVENTION
  - General
    - General and history, 1926-97, n.d. (Box 267, Folder 15)
    - Actions
      - Finance (Box 267, Folder 16)
      - Membership (Box 267, Folder 17)
    - Attendance statistics, 1958-1994 (incomplete) (Box 267, Folder 18)
    - Expenses incurred by the hostess city, 1920-38 (Box 268, Folder 1)
    - Planning and logistics, 1928-92, n.d. (Box 268, Folder 2)
    - Rules and regulations, 1951-75 (Box 268, Folder 3)
    - Organization Renewal Committee, Task Group on Convention as a decision-making body, 1969-72 (Box 268, Folder 4)
  - Conventions
    - 1st, 5-6 Dec 1906 (New York, NY), [see also Predecessor Organizations, Merger]
      - Program and other convention materials (Box 268, Folder 5)
      - Typed proceedings (Box 268, Folder 6)
      - Printed proceedings (Box 268, Folder 7)
    - 2nd, 22-26 Apr 1909 (St. Paul, Minnesota)
      - Reports and recommendations to (Box 269, Folder 1)
      - Program and other convention materials (Box 269, Folder 2)
      - Printed proceedings (Box 269, Folder 3)
      - Newspaper clippings (Box 269, Folder 4)
    - 3rd, 19-24 Apr 1911 (Indianapolis, Indiana)
      - Reports to (Box 269, Folder 5)
      - Program and other convention materials (Box 269, Folder 6)
      - Newspaper clippings (Box 269, Folder 7)
      - Publicity (Box 269, Folder 8)
    - 4th, 9-15 Apr 1913 (Richmond, Virginia)
      - Reports and recommendations to (Box 270, Folder 1)
      - Program and other convention materials (Box 270, Folder 2-3)
      - Printed proceedings (Box 270, Folder 4)
      - Newspaper clippings (Box 270, Folder 5)
    - 5th, 5-11 May 1915 (Los Angeles, California)
      - Reports and recommendations to (Box 270, Folder 6)
      - Program and other convention materials (Box 270, Folder 7-8)
      - Printed proceedings (Box 270, Folder 9)
      - Newspaper clippings (Box 270, Folder 10)
    - 6th, 13-20 Apr 1920 (Cleveland, Ohio)
      - Pre-Convention
        - General (Box 270, Folder 11)
        - Reports and recommendations to (Box 270, Folder 12)
      - Program and other convention materials (Box 270, Folder 13)
      - Printed proceedings and actions (Box 271, Folder 1)
      - Newspaper clippings (Box 271, Folder 2)
    - 7th, 20-27 Apr 1922 (Hot Springs, Arkansas)
      - Planning (Box 271, Folder 3)
      - Pre-Convention
        - General (Box 271, Folder 4)
        - Reports and recommendations to (Box 271, Folder 5)
      - Program and other convention materials (Box 271, Folder 6)
      - Printed proceedings and actions (Box 271, Folder 7)
      - Post-convention materials and Post Convention Committee (Box 271, Folder 8)
    - 8th, 30 Apr-6 May 1924 (New York City)
      - Pre-convention materials
        - General (Box 271, Folder 9-10)
        - Reports and recommendations to (Box 271, Folder 11)
      - Program and other convention materials (Box 271, Folder 12)
      - Printed proceedings and actions (Box 271, Folder 13)
    - 9th, 21-27 Apr 1926 (Milwaukee, Wisconsin)
      - Planning (Pre-Convention Committee) (Box 272, Folder 1)
      - Pre-convention materials
        - General (Box 272, Folder 2)
        - Reports and recommendations to (Box 272, Folder 3)
      - Program and other convention materials (Box 272, Folder 4)
      - Assemblies (Box 272, Folder 5)
      - Handbook for study and discussion (replaces Printed proceedings and actions) (Box 272, Folder 6)
    - 10th, 14-20 Apr 1928 (Sacramento, California)
      - Pre-convention materials
        - General (Box 272, Folder 7)
        - Reports to (Box 272, Folder 8)
      - Program and other convention materials (Box 272, Folder 9)
      - Printed proceedings and actions (Box 272, Folder 10)
      - Assemblies (Box 272, Folder 11)
    - 11th, 25 Apr-1 May 1930 (Detroit, Michigan)
      - Pre-convention materials
        - General (Box 273, Folder 1)
        - Reports to (Box 273, Folder 2)
      - Program and other convention materials (Box 273, Folder 3)
      - Assemblies (Box 273, Folder 4)
      - Printed proceedings and actions (Box 273, Folder 5)
    - 12th, 5-11 May 1932 (Minneapolis, Minnesota)
      - Planning (Box 273, Folder 6)
      - Pre-convention materials
        - General (Box 273, Folder 7)
        - Reports (Box 273, Folder 8)